Mss.B.H78 Mss.B.H78
American Philosophical Society
Materials for a biography, [ca. 1946-1962], of David Hosack
Circa 1946-1962
Mss.B.H78
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
David Hosack (1769-1835, APS 1810) was a physician and botanist active in medical education, as well as cultural life of New York City. Hosack founded Elgin Botanic Gardens, the first botanical gardens in America, co-founded the New York Historical Society and the short-lived Rutgers Medical School in New York City.
Ca. 300 items.
Robbins, Christine Chapman
Box 1-2
Scopte and Contents note
These materials include correspondence, notes, transcripts, and photostats of Hosack's correspondence compiled by Robbins for her biography, "David Hosack: Citizen of New York," APS Memoirs 62 (Philadelphia, 1964).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Christine Chapman Robbins and accessioned, 1961 (1961 1885ms). See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
David Hosack (1769-1835, APS 1810) was a physician and botanist active in medical education, as well as cultural life of New York City. Hosack founded Elgin Botanic Gardens, the first botanical gardens in America, co-founded the New York Historical Society and the short-lived Rutgers Medical School in New York City.
David Hosack was born in New York City. He started his education at Columbia College, but received his degree from the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University) in 1789. Hosack studied medicine under Nicholas Romayne, Philip Wright Post and Samuel Bard in New York; he then traveled to Philadelphia to study with Benjamin Rush. In 1791 he traveled to Scotland to continue studying medicine and botany.
Upon his return to America in 1795, Hosack became professor of botany at Columbia College a post he held in conjunction with the professorship of material medica until 1811. In 1797 Hosack went into practice with his former mentor Samuel Bard. Hosack was well respected by his patients, who often remarked that he went further than most other physicians to care to their comfort. In 1804 Hosack was the attending surgeon for the Burr-Hamilton duel. He attended Hamilton to the dueling place and cared for him for the subsequent 30 hours after he received his mortal wound.
Beyond his practice, Hosack was active in the medical profession. Together with his student, John W. Francis, Hosack established American Medical and Philosophical Register, which was published from 1810-1814. In 1826, Hosack founded the Rutgers Medical School of New York City, serving as president until 1830. And in 1820 Hosack was largely the driving force behind the founding of Bellvue Hospital.
Hosack’s interests outside of the medical profession were numerous. He established the Elgin Botanic Gardens, the first such gardens in America. He was a founder of the New York Historical Society, serving as president from 1820-1828. Hosack was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1810. Hosack married three times, and was widowed twice; he had 10 children. He died suddenly of apoplexy in 1835
Banks, Joseph, Sir, 1743-1820; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Eaton, Amos, 1776-1842; Hosack, David, 1769-1835; Park, Thomas, 1766-1844; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Biographies.; Physicians
- Papers
  - Letter to D. S. Dean, Oct. 7, 1801; B H78; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    Scope and Contents note
    New York, Photostat of A.L.S. 5p. (from original in Princeton university. see D. Hosack. Papers...; no.3.) Medicine.
  - Letter to Miss Bache, Philadelphia, May 4, 1821; B H78; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p.and add. (from original in Princeton university. see D.Hosack. Papers...; no.4.) The APS thanks her for Dr. Franklin's chair.
  - Letter to John Maclean, Princeton, Sept. 8, 1826; B H78; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. (from original in Princeton university. see D.Hosack. Papers..; no. 1.) Cannot make a talk to the society.
  - Letter to [Jesse] Buel, Albany, Jan. 20, 1831; B H78; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, Photostat of A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (from original in Princeton university. see D.Hosack. Papers...; no.2.) Botanical news.
  - Letter to the New York academy of medicine, Nov. 20, 1899; B H78.1; New York Botanical Garden
    Photostat of typed L.S.: N.L.Britton. 1p. (from original in N.Y.acad.of medicine) (see D.Hosack Papers.) Thanks for D.Hosack library books. Presented by Mrs.W.J.Robbins; April 1960.
  - Minutes, Jan. 5, 1899; B H78.2; New York Academy of Medicine
    Photostat of typed D. 4p. (from original in N.Y.academy of medicine.) (see D.Hosack papers.) Consists chiefly of the Library committee report. Presented by Mrs.W.J.Robbins; April 1960.
  - Letter to William Ludlow, Greenwich, Jan. 1, 1817; B H78.3; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see David Hosack Papers.) Sends bill for attendance, and asks payment.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, June 16, 1817; B H78.4; 9-3/4x7-3/4; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    New York, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Hosack papers.) Introduces Mr. Busby. Refers to Benjamin West.
  - Genealogical note pertaining to his family, Undated; B H78.5; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
  - Material used in writing on David Hosack, 1961; B H78.6; Robbins, Christine Chapman
    D. ca.100 leaves. Various sizes. Presented by Mrs. Robbins; Dec.1961.
  - Material collected by Mrs. Christine Robbins, 1810-1962; B H78.7; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    D. 131 letters, 8 photos.of letters, ca.20 leaves of working papers, and 25 photographs. Various sizes. Presented by Mrs. Robbins;Jan.9,1963.
  - Additions to the papers collected by Mrs. Robbins for her studies on David Hosack and John Torrey., Undated; B H78.8; Hosack, David, 1769-1835
    D.and copies of D. ca.35 items. Various sizes. Presented by Mrs. Christine C. Robbins; 1969.